<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<info>
<title>An AtomPub Server for MarkLogic Server</title>
<author>
<personname><firstname>Norman</firstname>
<surname>Walsh</surname>
</personname>
<email>norman.walsh@marklogic.com</email>
</author>
</info>

<para>The <link xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5023.txt">Atom
Publishing Protocol</link> is an application-level protocol for publishing and
editing entries in an
<link xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4287.txt">Atom Feed</link>.</para>

<para>The protocol's design centers around sending and receiving XML
representations of the resources. The Atom protocol server is expected
to maintain these collections of entries, respond to requests for
creating, retrieving, and updating them, and manage ancillary XML
representations that describe the services available to
clients.</para>

<para>These are all things that
<link xlink:href="http://www.marklogic.com/product/marklogic-server.html">MarkLogic
Server</link> was designed to do.</para>

<para>I decided to see how easy it would be to implement a fully conformant
Atom Publishing Protocol server in XQuery on top of MarkLogic Server. The answer:
remarkably easy. The entire implementation of the core server is less than
2000 lines of XQuery.</para>

<para>This distribution includes that core implementation plus a very
tiny weblog application designed to demonstrate how it could be used.
</para>

<section xml:id="manifest">
<title>What's in the distribution</title>

<para>The distribution consists of three parts:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>AtomPub</term>
<listitem>
<para>This is the code for the core server.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>WebLog</term>
<listitem>
<para>This is the code for the toy weblog implementation that
demonstrates the server.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>doc</term>
<listitem>
<para>This documentation.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section xml:id="how">
<title>How it works</title>

<para>If you're unclear about how the <citetitle>Atom Publishing
Protocol</citetitle> works, please read
<link xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5023.txt">the RFC</link>.
This section assumes that you have at least a passing familiarity with
AtomPub concepts.</para>

<para>Fundamentally, AtomPub is a simple protocol for interacting with
feed entries over HTTP. One of the interesting parts, with respect to
implementing a server, is dealing with security and authentication.</para>

<para>The goal is to interact with a Atom feed that publishes entries
that everyone can read. That means that we can't require authentication
to read the entries. At the same time, we don't want anyone to be able
to change the entries. That means that we must require authentication to
create, update, or delete entries.</para>

<para>There are many ways that we might accomplish this goal, but the
<citetitle>Atom Publishing Protocol</citetitle> mandates that we use
HTTP authentication for this purpose. That is, an AtomPub client will
expect to connect using standard HTTP authentication mechanisms.</para>

<para>The rub is that HTTP authentication doesn't distinguish between
kinds of access. Resource access either requires authentication or it
does not.</para>

<para>This means that there's no practical way to simultaneously use
standard HTTP authentication and allow read access to a resource without
authentication and write access with authentication.</para>

<para>Many AtomPub servers address this problem by providing two different
URIs to interact with the same resource: so
<uri>http://example.com/path/to/feed</uri> might provide read access without
authentication (and no write access at all), while
<uri>http://example.com/path/to/feed/edit</uri> might require authentication
and provide full access to authenticated clients.</para>

<para>We have to do the same thing. In our case the easiest way to do this
is to simple have two application servers (running on different ports, of course)
that access the same database: one supports full access with authentication
while the other supports only read access without authentication.</para>

<section xml:id="amps">
<title>Security Considerations</title>

<para>In addition to the users and roles created explicitly during
installation, the WebLog system adds users, roles, and privileges for
users when they register.</para>

<para>For each user, <replaceable>uname</replaceable>, registered,
the system creates:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A user named <replaceable>uname</replaceable>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A URI privilege named
<literal>weblog-edit-<replaceable>uname</replaceable></literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A role named
<literal>weblog-editor-<replaceable>uname</replaceable></literal>
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

</section>

<section xml:id="errhandler">
<title>The Error Handler</title>

<para>The toy WebLog makes extensive use of the error handler to deal
with requests for feeds which don't exist at precisely the URIs requested.</para>

<para>This code predates the addition of a URI rewriting mechanism in
MarkLogic Server. It's probably worth considering using the rewriter instead
of the error handler.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="alerting">
<title>Alerting</title>

<para>In a real WebLog, you might want to associate alerts with PUT
and POST events. Example code for accomplishing this is present (but
commented out) in <filename>/AtomPub/put.xqy</filename> and
<filename>/AtomPub/post.xqy</filename>.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="install">
<title>Installing the distribution</title>

<para>The following steps describe how to install and configure the
AtomPub server and the WebLog server. These instructions were designed
to be simple and straightforward, along the way we'll point out where
it might be useful to proceed with more care if you're deploying into
a production environment.</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Copy the <filename>AtomPub</filename> directory to
<filename>/opt/MarkLogic/Modules/</filename> (or wherever the modules
directory is on your system).</para>

<note>
<para>I wanted to make it possible for the WebLog application to
create new accounts automatically. Even in the testing phase, I didn't
really want to have to manually create users.
</para>

<para>But that introduces the circular problem of allowing
non-authenticated users to do something that's effectively an update
to the database.</para>

<para>The solution is to “amp” selected functions. For more
information, see <citetitle>19.0 Security Administration</citetitle>
in the <citetitle>MarkLogic Server Administrator's
Guide</citetitle>.</para>
</note>

<para>It's not possible to “amp” code that's
run from the filesystem, so you must put the AtomPub modules in the
servers module directory or in a a modules database.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Create roles. The system uses three roles: <literal>weblog-reader</literal>,
<literal>weblog-editor</literal>, and <literal>weblog-admin</literal>. These
roles exist mostly with an eye towards future extension, there isn't that
much difference between them today.
</para>

<para>The <literal>weblog-reader</literal> must have the following
execute privileges: <literal>unprotected-collections</literal>,
<literal>xdmp:add-response-header</literal>, and
<literal>xdmp:invoke</literal>. It must also have the
<literal>filesystem-access (read)</literal> capability.</para>

<para>The <literal>weblog-editor</literal> must inherit the
<literal>weblog-reader</literal> role.</para>

<para>The <literal>weblog-admin</literal> must inherit the
<literal>weblog-reader</literal> role and have the
<literal>unprotected-uri</literal> execute privilege.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Create users. You need to create two users, the rest will be created
automatically.</para>

<para>Create <literal>joepublic</literal> with the
<literal>weblog-reader</literal> role. This is the
user that will be used to access the unauthenticated, “read only”
server.</para>

<para>Create <literal>weblog-admin</literal> with the
<literal>weblog-admin</literal> role.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Create a “<literal>weblog</literal>” forest and
“<literal>weblog</literal>” database to hold the
feeds.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Create the public appserver on port 8600.</para>

<para>Specify the “<literal>atompub</literal>” database as the
database, the location where you installed the
“<filename>WebLog</filename>” directory as the root, use
“<literal>application-level</literal>” authentication with
“<literal>joepublic</literal> as the default user.
Specify <filename>/error-handler.xqy</filename> as the error
handler.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Create the authenticated appserver on port 8601.</para>

<para>Specify the “<literal>atompub</literal>” database as the
database, the location where you installed the
“<filename>WebLog</filename>” directory as the root, use
“<literal>basic</literal>” authentication (or any scheme that your
client supports) with
“<literal>nobody</literal> as the default user.
Specify <filename>/error-handler.xqy</filename> as the error
handler.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Create two “amps”, one for <function>create-putative-user</function>
and one for <function>create-user</function>. Both are in the
<uri>http://www.marklogic.com/modules/atompub/admin</uri> namespace
and have the document uri <uri>/AtomPub/admin.xqy</uri>.
</para>

<para>For convenience, just give them the “<literal>admin</literal>”
role. It would be possible to give them something more constrained in
production, but this is the easiest thing to do for testing.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Initialize the database with global configuration information.
</para>

<para>If you deviated from the instructions above, used different user names
or different ports, for example, then make sure you edit
<filename>/WebLog/setup/load-config.xqy</filename> before you run it!</para>

<para>When you're ready, log into the web server as
<literal>weblog-admin</literal> and run
<uri>/setup/load-config.xqy</uri>. This will setup some default
values.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section xml:id="configuration">
<title>Configuration</title>

<para>Global configuration information for the repository is stored in
<uri>/etc/configuration.xml</uri>. Here's what the default looks like:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
<configuration xmlns="http://www.marklogic.com/ns/atompub"
               xmlns:app="http://www.w3.org/2007/app"
   	    xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <root>http://localhost:8600</root>
  <edit-root>http://localhost:8601</edit-root>
  <generator>Mark Logic AtomPub V0.0.3</generator>
  <module method="post">/AtomPub/post.xqy</module>
  <module method="put">/AtomPub/put.xqy</module>
  <module method="validate">/AtomPub/validate.xqy</module>
  <module method="format">/AtomPub/format.xqy</module>
  <weblog-reader>joepublic</weblog-reader>
  <weblog-path>/u/</weblog-path>

  <reserved userid="admin"/>
  <reserved userid="weblog-admin"/>

  <user userid="ndw">
    <email>ndw@nwalsh.com</email>
    <title>Test Weblog</title>
  </user>

  <putative-user userid="newuser">
    <username>newuser</username>
    <password>password</password>
    <email>newuser@example.com</email>
    <title>My new weblog</title>
    <token>4615241119106240758</token>
  </putative-user>

</configuration>]]></programlisting>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><literal>root</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>This is the beginning of URIs that refer to unauthenticated feeds.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>edit-root</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>This is the beginning of URIs that refer to authenticated feeds.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>generator</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>This is the generator string that the server will place in feeds.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>module</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>There are four modules: post, put, format, and validate. Each module
identifies a query module that should be run to perform the indicated method.
The “post” and “put” methods are called for HTTP POST and PUT requests,
respectively. The “validate” module is called for any document being added
or updated, if it returns false the entry is rejected. The “format” module
is called when a normal user is reading a feed, it can translate from the
native feed format into HTML, for example.
</para>
<para>If you setup different collections, each collection can have its own
methods.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>weblog-reader</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>This is the name of the weblog reader account.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>weblog-path</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>This is the path to weblog entries. The format of URIs that point
to weblog entries is {root}{weblog-path}{username}.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>reserved</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>The code that allows users to add themselves to the database checks
for reserved accounts and will refuse to allow users to add accounts with
reserved names.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>user</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>For each user, we store their email address and the title of their weblog.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>putative-user</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>Putative users are ones who have done only the first half of the
registration process. When (if?) the second half of the registration
process is performed, we create an actual user in the security
database using the specified password, then we can forget it here.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section xml:id="testing">
<title>Testing the install</title>

<para>Navigate your browser to
<link xlink:href="http://localhost:8600/"/>. (Or whatever host and port you
used for the installation.) You should see a screen that looks like this:</para>

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="init.png"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<para>If you fill in the fields for “testuser” and click
<guibutton>Create</guibutton>, the server should respond:</para>

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="create.png"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<para>Clicking on “clicking here” will close the loop and finish creating
the account. (There's code in there for doing this by email, but it's
commented out.)</para>

<para>Now if you go back to the main screen on port 8600, you'll see the user
listed. If you point an AtomPub client at port 8601 and authenticate as
“<literal>testuser</literal>”, you should be able to edit the feeds!</para>
</section>

</article>
